<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Alex Mendiola: Coder - Posts</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/posts.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2019-06-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Personal Coding Bootcamp</title><link href="/Personal%20Coding%20Bootcamp.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Alex Mendiola</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-06-26:/Personal Coding Bootcamp.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Wherein I discuss my plans for summer coding competence...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am a high school English teacher by trade and my summer vacation has just begun. For the past couple of months I formulated plans to gain a working knowledge of software development. I selected Python as my initial language. I worked though the bulk of the Code with Mosh - Python for Developers course. And I added an SSD to my rig and installed Manjaro Linux for my development efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past two days, I built out my development setup on Manjaro and created this blog. It has been a struggle to develop a workflow for blogging that I feel will be efficient and effective. There are a few improvements to this blog that I have planned, but for now I need to get back to coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've quickly reviewed the majority of the course that I have already completed. Today, I'll finish that review. My schedule for this Personal Coding Bootcamp is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Monday - Friday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;8-8:30AM - Exercise&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;8:30-10:30AM - Coding&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;10:30-11AM - Break&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;11AM - 1PM - Coding&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;1-1:30PM - Lunch&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;1:30-6PM - House Projects/Maker Projects/Reading&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;2-4PM - optional 3rd coding block of 2 hours&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;6-7PM - Dinner&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;7-8PM - Gaming&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;8-8:30 - Blog&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;8:30 onward - Entertainment/Relaxation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the goal is 4-6 hours of coding each day with a separate 30 mins to update this blog. Let's see how this plan survives battle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Coding"></category><category term="Bootcamp"></category></entry><entry><title>Relative Paths</title><link href="/Relative%20Paths%20in%20VSCode%20on%20Windows.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Alex Mendiola</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-05-27:/Relative Paths in VSCode on Windows.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Issues with relative paths in VSCode on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I continue through the Python for Developers course offered by Mosh Hamedani, I noticed some odd behavior in Visual Studio Code. The relative paths that Mosh was describing returned an error in my code. At first, I solved the issue by creating a raw string. For instance,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Path&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;ecommerce&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;didn't work so I copied the full path and used the raw string.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Path&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sa"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;C:\Users\rig\coding\python\codeEnv\Mosh\ecommerce&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I realized later that I could use the relative path but I had to include the parent directory displayed in the file tab in Visual Studio Code. In my case...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Path&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Mosh\ecommerce&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;worked just fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you're using Windows and Visual Studio Code, be sure to include any parent directories in the file tab when writing relative paths in Visual Studio.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Python"></category><category term="Coding"></category></entry><entry><title>Successful Deployment of Blog</title><link href="/Successful%20Blog%20Deployment.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-23T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Alex Mendiola</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-05-23:/Successful Blog Deployment.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A brief post about how I deployed my blog using Pelican and Github&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, it only took several hours, but the blog is functional. I understand about 30% of the commands I typed into terminal (terminal is weird on Windows! Can't wait for the built in Linux Kernel). I've accepted this phase-state in my learning how to code. Most concepts are partially understood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that the blog is live and I am fairly confident I'll be able to update it regularly, a note about what you will find here: This will serve, at least initially, as a record of my learning path toward a career in software development/data science. So far, I've begun working through a course on Python for Developers. The last unit which covered lists, dictionaries, lambdas, comphrensions, etc. was particularly difficult. However, the final exercise in which I had to write an algorithm to determine the most frequent character in a string (e.g. "This is a common interview question") was partially solvable for me. I managed to create a program which will correctly solve the problem with any string. My code was not particularly efficient. Luckily, I have a good friend who works at Google. He took a look at my code and provided some interesting insights. First, I was not a total moron in my efforts. I used an extensive series of if statements (one for each letter of the alphabet) to get a count for each letter in the string. He did point out that it required several traversals of the string. This, with a large enough string/input would be memory intensive and provided some ideas to increase the efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He mentioned ord() and xrange() both of which I had not yet encountered. This certainly set me at ease. At least I had not overlooked a simple solution which I had already been taught. My ignorance did not impede my ability to solve the problem!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll continue to forge ahead in the course and call on my mentor at Google should I encounter any other obstacles that Stack Overflow and Google cannot provide the necessary insight. And of course I will continue to update my progress here. Once I begin building code, I will post it to github as well. Perhaps with a few more weeks of concentrated study I will be able to give back to the community in some meaningful way... or not... the jury is still out on whether or not I've got the chops for this racket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Alex&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>